<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord-Mayor, and Aldermen of the city of London, at St. Mary Le Bow on Wednesday the 19th of June, 1695, a day appointed for a solemn fast, for supplicating Almighty God for the pardon of our sins, and imploring his protection of His Majestie's person, by Josiah Woodward ...</title>
            <author>Woodward, Josiah, 1660-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67018</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3520</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23478</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12764925</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12764925</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93565</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67018)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93565)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 994:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord-Mayor, and Aldermen of the city of London, at St. Mary Le Bow on Wednesday the 19th of June, 1695, a day appointed for a solemn fast, for supplicating Almighty God for the pardon of our sins, and imploring his protection of His Majestie's person, by Josiah Woodward ...</title>
                  <author>Woodward, Josiah, 1660-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ralph Simpson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:93565:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93565:1"/>
            <p>Mr. Woodward's SERMON before the Lord-Mayor, On the Faſt-Day, <hi>June</hi> the <hi>19<hi rend="sup">th,</hi>
               </hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:93565:2"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>Lane <hi>Mayor.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Jovis 20 <hi>die Junij,</hi> 1695. Anno<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> 
                     <hi>Dom. Reg.</hi> Gulielmi <hi>tertij</hi> Ang. &amp;c. <hi>Septimo.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Court doth deſire Mr. <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> to Print his Sermon Preached yeſterday at the Pariſh-Church of St. <hi>Mary Le Bow,</hi> before the Right Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Goodfellow.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93565:2"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before The Right Honourable the Lord-Mayor, AND ALDERMEN OF THE City of London, At St. <hi>Mary Le BOW;</hi> On <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the <hi>19th</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> 1695. A Day appointed for a Solemn Faſt, for Supplicating Almighty God for the Pardon of our Sins; and imploring his Protection of His Majeſtie's Perſon, and the Proſperity of His Arms by Sea and Land. By Order of the Lords Juſtices.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Joſiah Woodward,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Poplar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ralph Simpſon</hi> at the <hi>Harp</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93565:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93565:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE Right Honourable Sir</hi> Thomas Lane, <hi>Lord Mayor of the City of</hi> London, <hi>AND THE</hi> Court of ALDERMEN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>INCE nothing in the following Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe can be ſuppoſed to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended it to the Hearers, but thoſe ſerious and ſeaſonable Truths, whereby it <hi>recommends it ſelf to every Man's Conſcience.</hi> It muſt be look'd on as a Specimen of your Lordſhip's and your Worſhipful Brethren's Integrity towards God, and Fidelity to the preſent Government (in a time when ſome ſo eaſily ſhake hands with both together) That you deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view what was humbly offered upon our late Faſt-Day, on thoſe two Topicks (of Duty <hi>to God</hi> and the <hi>King;)</hi> which the <hi>Nature</hi> of the Things, and
<pb facs="tcp:93565:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> the <hi>Duty</hi> of the Day entwiſted together. And may theſe Heaven-born Twinns never be devided upon Earth: For indeed, they are but half-Friends (if we may not call them Enemies) to any <hi>Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> who are impatient of the <hi>Government of God;</hi> by whoſe Bleſſing alone <hi>Kingdoms</hi> Flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. The ſins of ſuch Perſons <hi>hurt</hi> the ſide they take, more than their Aſſiſtance helps it.</p>
            <p>And therefore, when all is done; <hi>unfeigned Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi> (how lightly ſoever eſteemed in theſe filthy dreggs of time) is ſurely the moſt Honourable and uſeful accompliſhment of Humane Nature. The real <hi>Servant of God</hi> is the true <hi>Perſon of Quality,</hi> being one of the <hi>Houſehold of God.</hi> And till any <hi>Empire</hi> can be found equal to that of <hi>God;</hi> no <hi>Title</hi> or <hi>Employment</hi> can be of equivalent Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to that of belonging to the <hi>Court of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet we ſee, the World laughs at this. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Notions of ſome, there is Glory in the ſervice of the Devil. And the moſt like him in <hi>Pride, Falſehood, Revenge,</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> are the fineſt Men. But, are not theſe very horrible and very perverſe Sentiments? Has <hi>Bedlam</hi> it ſelf any ſuch reverſe to common ſenſe, as this? And will not inſupportable ſhame ſucceed this <hi>Phrenzy,</hi> when once they come to ſee things in a true light? And
<pb facs="tcp:93565:4"/> this they will ſee to the purpoſe, within a little while, either in their <hi>Converſion</hi> or <hi>Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. God Almighty</hi> grant it them in the firſt Method, not in the laſt.</p>
            <p>It is not more evident that the Sun guilds and cheers this lower World, than that Religion is the <hi>Light, Glory,</hi> and <hi>Advancement</hi> of the Intellect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ual part of it. Happy are its <hi>Votaries,</hi> yea bleſſed are its very <hi>Martyrs.</hi> It is a very light thing to bear the mockery and Affronts of this World, if we do but paſs on directly to the Glory of the other. Thoſe that are <hi>blind</hi> will be apt to joſtle thoſe they meet in the ſtreets: But it is the Duty of ſuch as ſee, to endeavour to put them into the right way.</p>
            <p>And therefore, there is no Poſt beneath the Clouds ſo honourable, as that of a <hi>Perſon</hi> in great <hi>Power,</hi> employing it to reclaim and <hi>reform the Community</hi> to which it belongs. It is like the <hi>Good Angel</hi>'s leading <hi>Lot</hi> and his Family out of the reach of the deſcending Flames. The comforts of which here is almoſt as inexpreſſible as it's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the whole, if there be any ſuch <hi>Great and Bleſſed Man</hi> (or ſet of Men) upon Earth: <hi>by</hi> whoſe Piety, Prudence, and Power (under God) <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> is to retrieve its Credit, and <hi>God</hi> his Honour in the World. <hi>Bleſſed</hi> is He (or They)
<pb facs="tcp:93565:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> above the common rate of <hi>Mortals!</hi> All the ſober part of <hi>Mankind</hi> will kiſs their feet, and the moſt remote Poſterity will bleſs their <hi>Memory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confide, <hi>My Lord,</hi> That your juſt indignation to the <hi>wretched Atheiſm</hi> of this prophane Age will incline your Lordſhip to excuſe the Prolixity of this Addreſs to you; to which ſhall now put a ſpeedy Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod, ſo ſoon as I have implored this one mercy of God, <hi>viz.</hi> That your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> and your <hi>Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Brethren,</hi> may by your pious and prudent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, eſtabliſh the Peace, reſtore the Piety, and advance the Proſperity and Renown of this Great and Famous City: And hereby aſcertain to your ſelves abiding Manſions in that City which has <hi>Divine Foundations:</hi> which is the unfeigned Deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>your Lordſhip's very Reſpectful Humble Servant,</hi> Joſhiah Woodward.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93565:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Deut. IX. 26.</bibl>
               <q>I Prayed therefore unto the Lord, and ſaid, O Lord God, deſtroy not thy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and thine Inheritance, which thou haſt redeemed thro' thy greatneſs: which thou haſt brought forth of Egypt with a mighty hand.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Solemn Duty of every Soul of us this Day (but more eſpecially of all <hi>Publick Perſons)</hi> is the ſame with that of <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Text; <hi>viz:</hi> Humbly to importune our offended God, for mercy to a ſinful People. And this, in the me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thod of <hi>Faſting and Prayer,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> here did Yea, the Parallel runs further in that about this time the <hi>Armies of Iſrael</hi> were to Attack their Enemies in <hi>their Entrenchments and Fenced Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> as we read at the beginning of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>Hear, O Iſrael, thou art to paſs over Jordan this day, to go in to poſſeſs Nations greater and</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:93565:6"/> 
               <hi>mightier than thy ſelf: Cities great and fenced up to Heaven,</hi> v. 1. <hi>i. e.</hi> Very ſtrongly Fortified, ſo as to be impregnable by any Forces but ſuch as were led on by the <hi>Lord of Hoſts.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he takes this occaſion to ſhew them the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſſity of making their peace with God, and ſecuring his powerful Alliance. And may we (in a like juncture) prudently take the Hint.</p>
            <p>But here the Parallel diſcontinues; <hi>viz.</hi> In that <hi>Moſes</hi> here had but one ſingle Enormity of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (tho' a very great one) to lament before God: and that too, was happily nipt in the bud, by an <hi>impartial execution of Juſtice on the known Offenders,</hi> Exod. 32. 27. But our Sins, alas! are prodigiouſly many as well as great: And theſe too are fatally ripen'd by long indulgence and impunity. So that our Breach is very wide, and we need many ſuch as <hi>Moſes to ſtand in the Gap</hi> and fill it up, which I pray God raiſe up to us in this important Juncture, in which the very Being of our Church and Nation lies at ſtake. May the good God pour out a <hi>Spirit of Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Supplication</hi> on us, that every Soul this day may put it ſelf out to the utmoſt in the proper work of it: <hi>i. e.</hi> Humiliation and Prayer. And bleſſed be God who giveth us this day ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93565:6"/> ſeaſon of interceſſion for mercy, before the final execution of his vengeance. For, it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite mercy alone that has ſuſpended our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction thus long, when our ſins have <hi>ſo long and ſo loudly cry'd for it.</hi> And ſurely this ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion of God's wrath gives us room to hope, that it is the <hi>waiting of his Goodneſs to be gracious to us.</hi> We truſt that the door of Divine Mercy is not yet nailed up againſt us, by ſuch a ſevere Decree as that which is thrice mention'd <hi>(Ezek.</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 14, 18, 20.) that tho' thoſe three Favourites Heaven, <hi>Noah, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Job</hi> ſtood up in the behalf of that People, they could not turn away God's wrath from them.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore <hi>cry mightily to God</hi> this Day, humbly pouring out our melted Souls before him, according to the <hi>Example of Moſes</hi> in the Text. And God Almighty grant that our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers may find the ſame acceptance as that of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> did. To this end, let us pray with his Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency, and Integrity; and ſay, <hi>O Lord God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy not thy People and thine Inheritance which thou haſt redeemed thro' thy greatneſs, which thou haſt brought forth of Egypt with a mighty hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Book of <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> is a brief Rehearſal of the moſt <hi>Memorable Paſſages</hi> which occurr'd to the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> under the Conduct of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93565:7"/> 
               <hi>Moſes;</hi> with very <hi>ſuitable and ſerious applications</hi> all along.</p>
            <p>The Text touches upon their great Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion in the <hi>matter of the Golden Calf,</hi> a Sin of very great provocation, and had been of as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Conſequence, had not <hi>Moſes</hi> with the deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt humiliation, and earneſtneſs, like that of Wreſtling <hi>Jacob,</hi> cry'd and interceded for them, as in the Text, <hi>I Prayed therefore unto the Lord,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In which words, theſe two Obſervations are obvious to every conſiderate Mind, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. That times of great provocation ſhould be to all the Faithful Servants of God, a ſeaſon of earneſt and extraordinary interceſſion with him. <hi>Iſrael</hi> falls to Idolatry and Profaneneſs: and <hi>Moſes</hi> throws himſelf down before the Lord, to aſſwage his Wrath, and ſolicit his mercy. <hi>I prayed therefore unto the Lord,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That a People's profeſſion of the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and being thoſe which God has ſignally delivered and defended in times paſt, may make an humble Plea with God for farther Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. <hi>Deſtroy not thy People and thine Inheritance which thou haſt redeemed thro' thy greatneſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the firſt place, let us take notice; That times of great wickedneſs and provocation ſhould
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93565:7"/> be a ſeaſon for good People's earneſt and aſſidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Interceſſion with God. The greater the ſin of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was, the longer and the more earneſtly did <hi>Moſes</hi> cry to God for Mercy towards them.</p>
            <p>A People are not in the laſt extremity, whilſt they have a <hi>Moſes</hi> left among them. A Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Zealous Interceſſor ſtands a People in great ſtead in time of Wrath. Inſomuch that when God fully determines to deſtroy any People, he firſt ſtops the mouths of Interceſſors. As (Jer. 7. 16.) <hi>Pray not thou for this People, neither lift up Cry nor Prayer for them, neither make interceſſion for them, for I will not hear thee.</hi> And in this very caſe of the <hi>Golden Calf,</hi> tho' at the firſt there ſeem'd little hope of obtaining mercy with God, when he ſaid in his anger to <hi>Moſes, Let me alone that I may conſume them,</hi> Exod. 32. 10. Yet after <hi>Moſes</hi>'s humble and earneſt Prayer in the Text, it had this effect: <hi>That the Lord repented of the evil which he thought to do unto his People,</hi> Exod. 32. 14. Yet they were not to come off clear, without many a blow of Correction for this Fault, as they were told, <hi>(v.</hi> 34.) <hi>Nevertheleſs in the day when I viſit, I will viſit their ſin upon them.</hi> When God took up the Rod to laſh them on other occaſions, he gave them a blow or two the more for this, which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93565:8"/> the <hi>Jews</hi> knew very well; inſomuch that in moſt of their Sufferings afterwards, they uſed to ſay, <hi>that there was a hair of the Golden Calf in them.</hi> But ſtill it was the Chyrurgeons Launce, not the Executioner's Ax. And this was happily procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by means of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Interceſſion: And that in this method.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. He falls down before the Lord.</item>
               <item>2. He Faſts Forty days and Forty nights.</item>
               <item>3. He Prays with great Fervour, and a ſort of undeniable urgency for the Publick Good.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, He falls down before the Lord. This is twice mentioned in the verſe before the Text, <hi>v.</hi> 25. By which muſt be meant, either that he fell down on his Knees, or more probably on his Face before the Lord: as he did <hi>(Numb.</hi> 16. 22.) And as our bleſſed Saviour himſelf did <hi>(Mat.</hi> 26. 39.) Which ſhews us, that reverence of bodily geſture is very requiſite in the ſolemn Worſhip of God. Methinks I cannot imagine how any ſober Perſon can think otherwiſe, or chuſe to do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. Our Bodies are an Eſſential part of our ſelves, and we expect to be glorified in them as well as in our Souls; and therefore we ought <hi>to glorifie God in our Souls and in our Bodies which are his,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 20. We muſt indeed firſt and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally look to the Compoſure and Frame of our
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93565:8"/> Hearts: And then (where no impediment pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents us) we ought to diſpoſe our Bodies too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a very reverend and humble poſture, that one part of us may not ſeem to diſallow and undo that which the other is doing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Moſes</hi> Faſts Forty Days and Forty Nights, being miraculouſly ſupported; for he kept a very ſtrict Faſt, as he deſcribes it <hi>(v.</hi> 18.) <hi>I did neither eat bread nor drink water,</hi> being earneſtly intent on the work in hand. Now, tho' we cannot imitate this for ſo many days, yet methinks ſuch as are healthy may well bear it for one day. Not that there is any Spiritual Holineſs in the bare Act of Faſting any more than in Eating; but that it better conduces to the proper work of a day of Humiliation, and is indeeed a natural expreſſion of ſelf-abhorrency, and of the inward bitterneſs and affliction of the Soul. If we have loſt a dear Relation, <hi>we forget to eat our bread,</hi> and all our uſual refreſhments are inſipid to us: And ſurely it cannot be otherwiſe, when we are duly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd, that by our wickedneſs we are like to ſin away our God, our Mercies, our Eternal Bliſs. The Prophet ſpeaking of the ſorrow of Penitents, ſays, <hi>They ſhall mourn as one that mourneth for his only Son: and be in bitterneſs, as one that is in bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs for his firſt-born,</hi> Zech. 12. 10.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:93565:9"/>
            <p> This, this, my Brethren, is our proper Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour this day. We are to lament <hi>crying Sins,</hi> and <hi>departing Mercies,</hi> yea, I fear, a <hi>departing God.</hi> Let this engage our hearts in a more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious diſcharge of the duties of this day than is uſual. As for ſuch as give their minds to bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs or vanity in the Mornings of our <hi>Faſt-days,</hi> and after this come coldly and unaffectedly to the publick Service of God, and thence return to their uſual meals, and ſpend the reſt of the day as impertinently (ſhall I ſay? or rather as provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kingly) as this; I cannot but ask them in the words of the Prophet <hi>(Iſa.</hi> 58. 5.) <hi>Is this the Faſt which God has choſen?</hi> Wilt thou call ſuch idleneſs as this <hi>an acceptable day to the Lord?</hi> Alas! what wretched notions haſt thou of the Great God? if thou thinkeſt him pleaſed with the skin of a Sacrifice? What ſenſe of his Glorious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty? His Spiritual and Holy Nature? His Infinite Glory and Ubiquity? If thou ſetteſt ſo light by his Service and Preſence?</p>
            <p>If any one had greatly offended you, and came to you to ask your pardon, and to lament his fault; ſhould he now come fleering and laughing into your preſence, and preſently ſet him down on his Seat, and talk of ſomething elſe, and do nothing but toy and trifle whilſt he is with you;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93565:9"/> would you not ſay, this Fellow came hither on purpoſe to <hi>mock me and defie me?</hi> I am more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by his <hi>ſham-repentance,</hi> than by his <hi>firſt fault.</hi> But, alas! what is a ſlight done to us poor ſinful Duſt, if compared to mockery done to the Almighty God? Ah, Sirs! <hi>be not deceived, God will not (cannot) be mock'd, Gal.</hi> 6. 7. Our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal and ineffectual Faſts do rather kindle God's wrath than encline his mercy. Faſts, did I ſay? the common obſervance of theſe days by ſome People deſerves not that name. There's not ſo much as the likeneſs and outward appearance of a Faſt in many places. The ſame concourſe in the Streets, the ſame throng in Publick Houſes, and diverſion in the Fields; the ſame Ornaments, and Meals, and Mirth as on other days; and the ſame idleneſs and indevotion. Oh! that I could awaken the <hi>drouzy Conſciences</hi> of theſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or at leaſt their <hi>care of decency;</hi> for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon abuſes of theſe Solemn Days are to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horr'd and hiſs'd at, by all that have any ſenſe of <hi>Religion,</hi> or indeed any due regard to <hi>Civil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum.</hi> The Faſts of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> are grave, ſevere, and devout <hi>Solemnities,</hi> and ſhall the Faſts of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> be trifling, vain, and unſincere? God forbid.</p>
            <p>Let us then ſeek the Lord this day with all our Soul, and this in a ſerious, contrite, and ſelf-abaſing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93565:10"/> manner: which leads me to the third thing remarkable in the behaviour of <hi>Moſes</hi> on this occaſion, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. He Prays with great fervour, and with a ſort of undeniable urgency for the publick good, <q>I Prayed therefore unto the Lord and ſaid, Oh Lord God, deſtroy not thy People, and thine Inheritance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As if he ſaid, let not thy wrath, good God, conſume that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which has the Divine honour to be called <hi>thine,</hi> and to bear thy Name. They are thy <hi>peculiar People,</hi> for whoſe ſake thou haſt wrought ſuch glorious Miracles; ſuch as no People but they were ever favoured withall. This is that People which thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs redeemed from the ſlavery of <hi>Egypt,</hi> in which Deliverance thou didſt <hi>make bare thine Almighty Arm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> And now, O Lord, ſhall thy <hi>vengeance</hi> cut down thoſe whom thy <hi>mercy</hi> has ſo lately raiſed up? Wilt thou deſtroy thoſe in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> for whom thou ſhewedſt ſuch tenderneſs in <hi>Egypt?</hi> Will not the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> blaſpheme thy name, and the <hi>Egyptians</hi> triumph, when they ſhall hear of this? and ſay, that thou deſtroyedſt this People becauſe thou couldſt not perform thy Promiſes made to them. Permit, <hi>O Mighty Jehovah,</hi> I pray
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93565:10"/> thee, permit a poor ſinful worm to lay this humble Expoſtulation at the Footſtool of thy <hi>Mercy Seat:</hi> Not to inſtruct my <hi>Maker</hi> (who knoweth all things) but to expreſs my earneſt zeal for the <hi>glory</hi> of thy Name, and the <hi>good</hi> of thy People.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This is the Scope of this Pious Man's Prayer in the Text, which was not put up in vain: For it averted imminent wrath, and obtained ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Mercy. Now as the Example of <hi>Elijah</hi>'s <hi>Prayer</hi> (by which the Heavens were opened and ſhut) is propoſed to us for our encouragement by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> (Jam. 5. 17.) ſo may we here enliven both our Affections and our Hopes from the Example of <hi>praying and prevailing Moſes</hi> in the Text. Days of Faſting ought to be days of extraordinary Prayer and Interceſſion. A real Chriſtian cannot do otherwiſe, his concern for the honour of God is mightily rowz'd up by the perfidiouſneſs and Apoſtacy of others. And on this occaſion, <hi>Zeal</hi> for God, <hi>Compaſſion</hi> to Men, and <hi>Indignation</hi> againſt Sin, will make him put himſelf out to the utmoſt. As when a Valiant <hi>Heroick General</hi> ſees ſome of his <hi>Troops</hi> quitting their ſtation, and fleeing in Battle: He bravely oppoſes the retiring Crowd, throws himſelf into the chiefeſt place of danger, and valiantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93565:11"/> that ground which others had baſely quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And thus ſometimes the ſingle valour of one <hi>brave Commander</hi> wins the day.</p>
            <p>Thus ſeaſonably did <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtep in to the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour of the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when otherwiſe the breach of their integrity (like a breach made in the ranks of an Army) had opened a paſſage to the conſuming wrath of God amongſt them. And by this <hi>Moſes</hi> is ſaid to <hi>ſtand up in the breach,</hi> without which <hi>they had been deſtroyed, Pſal</hi> 106. 23. and this <hi>Moſes</hi> did very often. For,</p>
            <p>When <hi>Corah</hi> and <hi>his Accomplices</hi> had generaly miſled the People into an execrable Sedition. And for this, God had kindled a dreadful Plague among them: With what earneſtneſs did this good man direct <hi>Aaron</hi> to make a ſpeedy attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for them! <hi>Take a Cenſer</hi> (ſays he) <hi>and put fire therein from off the Altar, and put on In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, and go quickly into the Congregation, and make attonement for them, for the Plague is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun</hi> Numb. 16. 46. And this <hi>Aaron</hi> did (whilſt <hi>Moſes lay on his face v.</hi> 22.) ſeeking mercy for them and ſo theſe two pious Interceſſors ſtood as a Bulwark <hi>betwixt the dead and the living,</hi> and ſtop'd the progreſs of God's wrath for that time alſo. But this powerful interceſſion of <hi>Moſes</hi> never was ſo clearly ſeen as in the <hi>Battel with</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:93565:11"/> 
               <hi>Amalek, Exod.</hi> 17. 11. where <hi>Moſes</hi> no ſooner <hi>ſunk his devout hands,</hi> but the Victory of <hi>Iſrael declined,</hi> with them, and fell to the other ſide, as if the Victory and power of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had been chain'd to his arm; by which it pleaſed God to give them a demonſtration of what importance the prayers of this one <hi>eminent Servant</hi> of his was to them.</p>
            <p>Thus did <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the <hi>Elders of Iſrael,</hi> when their Forces had been diſcomfited before the People of <hi>Ai. They rent their cloaths, and fell on their faces to the earth, and put duſt upon their heads, and prayed earneſtly to the Lord,</hi> and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained favour in his ſight, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 2. 6. Thus did <hi>Abraham, Samuel, Jehoſaphat, Joſiah, Ezra, Daniel,</hi> and all the eminent Servants of God in all Ages, whoſe devout prayers have frequently ſcattered thoſe black Clouds which the common guilt had raiſed, which otherwiſe had faln in a dreadful ſtorm upon their heads.</p>
            <p>Oh! that this throng of Holy <hi>Precedents</hi> might be effectual to excite our moſt elevated Devotions this day. Let us indeed afflict our Souls before the All-ſeeing God; leſt our <hi>mock-Faſts</hi> make work for <hi>real ones;</hi> and leſt we <hi>haſten</hi> that wrath which we ſeem to <hi>deprecate.</hi> Let us indeed do the needful work of <hi>Interceſſors</hi> with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93565:12"/> God; and that we may not want Arguments to plead for mercy, the latter part of my Text will ſuggeſt ſomething appoſite to our Caſe, which is ſummed up in my ſecond obſervation, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That a <hi>Peoples</hi> profeſſion of the <hi>true Religion,</hi> and being thoſe whom God had ſignally <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd</hi> and defended in times paſt, may be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pleaded with God as an argument for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Deliverance.</hi> For thus <hi>Moſes</hi> prays and pleads in the Text. <hi>O Lord, deſtroy not thy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and thine Inheritance which thou haſt redeemed thro' thy Greatneſs, which thou haſt brought forth of the Land of Egypt with a mighty hand.</hi> In which he ſeems to argue thus. <q>Oh Lord, may it pleaſe thee to make the procedure of thy <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> towards this <hi>People</hi> ſuitable to what it has been hitherto. Thou haſt hitherto pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and defended them by <hi>aſtoniſhing diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations.</hi> We can never forget that dreadful ſucceſſion of <hi>miraculous Plagues</hi> which thou broughteſt upon our <hi>Enemies the Egyptians:</hi> How <hi>groſly</hi> thou didſt infatuate them, and how <hi>eminently</hi> thou didſt inſpirit us, and by what a wonderful Revolution thou waſt pleaſed to <hi>free us</hi> from their ſlavery. Oh Let us not now periſh by that <hi>powerful hand</hi> by which we were
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93565:12"/> ſo lately delivered. 'Tis true, we are guilty of great provocations, but thy <hi>mercy</hi> is greater than our perverſeneſs. Oh ſpare a very ſinful <hi>People for thine infinite mercy ſake.</hi> Leſt when the <hi>Egyptians</hi> hear of our deſtruction, they triumph in our ruine in the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> as much as we did in the deſtruction of the <hi>Egyptians in the Red Sea.</hi> Yea, leſt they think thy power oftner diſplayed in <hi>Judgment</hi> than in <hi>Mercy.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This is the purport of the Plea in my <hi>Text,</hi> which may be reduced to theſe four Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He pleads for mercy for them, on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their relation to God, as they were his People; <hi>Deſtroy not thy People and thine Inheritance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They were a <hi>peculiar People</hi> by a very ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and ſelecting love of God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 43. <hi>Hath God eſſayed to go and take him a Nation from the midſt of another Nation, by Signs, Wonders, and by a mighty hand, as the Lord your God did you,</hi> &amp;c. So that now the honour of God ſeemed to be concerned for their preſervation.</p>
            <p>Now, all that profeſs the incorrupt <hi>Religion of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> may form an Argument ſomewhat like this, and ſay, <q>Lord, we are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> we cleave to the <hi>Doctrine of thy Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Son,</hi> for his ſake, whoſe Name we bear, and for the honour of thy <hi>viſible Church</hi> on Farth, deſtroy us not. And, tho' (alas!) too
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93565:13"/> too few of us are duly influenced by our <hi>holy Faith,</hi> yet we generally avow thee, thee alone to be our God, in oppoſition to <hi>Idols and other Gods.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Oh that we could ſay we are <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> and <hi>Prophaneneſs</hi> too, then our plea would be irreſiſtible.</p>
            <p n="2">II. There may be a further plea inferr'd from <hi>Moſes his Prayer</hi> thus, <hi>viz.</hi> For as much as there is ſeldom the profeſſion of the true <hi>Religion</hi> without ſome hearty and entire embracers of it. So that an Argument may be made like that of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s, Gen. 18. 24. <hi>If there be Fifty, or Forty, or but Ten Righteous Perſons,</hi> wilt thou not ſpare the corrupt generality for the ſake of this little ſound part? This, we have great hope, may be pleaded in the behalf of <hi>this Nation,</hi> yea of <hi>this City.</hi> Even in a far greater Number than that which <hi>Abraham</hi> began his Plea with. But truly the number of the Good is too too ſmall: And indeed, <hi>except the Lord had left unto us, this ſmall Remnant, we had been altogether as Sodom and like unto Gomorrah,</hi> Iſa. 1. 9 But we truſt we ſhall fare the better for the ſake of theſe.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Another part of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s <hi>Plea</hi> is ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the paſt Mercies which God had vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaf'd to this People. <hi>This is the People</hi> (ſays he)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93565:13"/> 
               <hi>which thou haſt redeemed thro' thy greatneſs, and brought out of Egypt with thy mighty hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this reſpect alſo ſome Plea may be made for <hi>England.</hi> It is a Land which God has by a <hi>Series of Wonders</hi> freed from the <hi>Slavery and Corruptions</hi> of <hi>Popery.</hi> An infinite Bleſſing which we have now enjoy'd for almoſt two Centuries of Years. And tho' there have been many Combinations and reſtleſs Plottings againſt us; yet, bleſſed be God, they have hitherto proved abortive: And we are at this day (thro' infinite mercy) a <hi>Free People,</hi> enjoying the <hi>bleſſed Beams of the Goſpel,</hi> and the Juſt and <hi>Antient Rights</hi> of our <hi>Mother-Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O! may that <hi>Bountiful God</hi> who has hitherto thus ſeaſonably, thus marvelouſly appeared for us, ſtill be our <hi>Guardian.</hi> May his <hi>infinite Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> never leave us, but flow down with the ſame exuberant Streams on us, and our Poſterity to the lateſt Generations. So that we may here ſay as <hi>Solomon; The Lord our God be with us as He was with our Fathers; let him not leave us nor forſake us,</hi> 1 Kings 8. 57.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Another part of <hi>Moſes his Plea</hi> is taken from the Inſolence of the Enemy, <hi>ver.</hi> 28. <hi>Leſt the Land whence thou broughteſt us out, ſay; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord was not able to bring them into the</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:93565:14"/> 
               <hi>Land which he promiſed them, and becauſe he hated them, he hath brought them out to ſlay them in the Wilderneſs.</hi> The World is apt to judge of the goodneſs of the Cauſe by its ſucceſs, and to make very wild Interpretations of the <hi>Language of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence.</hi> Wicked men are apt to conclude that God is on their ſide, when their Miſchievous De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns take effect. So that on this account alſo we may form a Plea for Mercy: For, if <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> be conſumed, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> will be ſure to glory in their Ruine, as in the Fall of <hi>Miſcreant Hereticks:</hi> Eſpecially, ſince their <hi>Cardinal Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion</hi> makes <hi>outward Proſperity and Victory</hi> the mark of his ſplendid <hi>Church</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ultima No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta eſt faelicitas temporalis, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitùs ijs collata qui Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derunt.</hi> Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min de Notis Eccleſiae, cap. 18.</note> Which, by his leave, would better have fitted the mouth of a <hi>Turk</hi> than a <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> For, <hi>Mahomet</hi> propoſed to propagate his Faith by the Sword, which our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour</hi> never did, but the very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, ſince the <hi>French Papiſts</hi> have ſo glutted themſelves already with the groans and blood of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in their own Country; ſhould their bloody Deſigns againſt us proſper too, how would they blaſpheme the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> and triumph in their own <hi>Deluſions?</hi> May the <hi>Lord of Armies</hi> therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feeble
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93565:14"/> the Power, and blaſt the Deſigns of thoſe <hi>Maſſacring Legions.</hi> And if our ſins are ſo ripe, that <hi>Infinite Juſtice</hi> can ſpare us no longer, nor <hi>infinite patience</hi> any longer ſuſpend our puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>may we fall into the hands of God rather than Men.</hi> Rather the <hi>Peſtilence,</hi> or <hi>Scarcity,</hi> or any <hi>earthly Plague;</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 14. (as <hi>David</hi> once choſe) than fall into the hands of <hi>bloody bigotted Papiſts,</hi> their very <hi>mercies</hi> are bitterly <hi>cruel,</hi> like <hi>Belzebub</hi> himſelf, they <hi>mock</hi> while they <hi>torment.</hi> For, whilſt they are racking our <hi>Bodies</hi> with exquiſite tortures, they pretend it to be a high piece of Charity to our <hi>Souls.</hi> 'Tis this makes the <hi>French</hi> ſay, that they have treated their <hi>Country-men</hi> of the <hi>Reformed Religion</hi> with great kindneſs, and that there has been no <hi>Perſecution</hi> amongſt them: tho' they have exerciſed them with all the trying and tedious methods of Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty that their <hi>Dragoons</hi> (aſſiſted by <hi>infernal ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice)</hi> could invent, or execute.</p>
            <p>Should the Friends of the <hi>French Intereſt</hi> here but taſte a few drops of this <hi>bitter Cup</hi> (after which they ſeem to long; and could they drink it alone, none would grudge it them) it would ſoon cool their unreaſonable paſſion for it. For, till <hi>Popery</hi> can entirely deſtroy our Reaſon, and bewitch our ſenſes (as it pretends to do) we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93565:15"/> but account <hi>Romiſh Darkneſs</hi> and <hi>Romiſh Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very</hi> the very quinteſſence of the <hi>Egyptian Plagues,</hi> and the moſt comprehenſive miſeries above Hell. For they contain moſt of the <hi>Plagues</hi> of this Life, both Temporal and Spiritual, with an execrable tendency to the remedileſs <hi>Torments</hi> of the Life to come.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, as the <hi>Jews</hi> met with many Deliverances, meerly to keep their <hi>Adverſaries</hi> from vaunting, may it pleaſe God to vouchſafe us the ſame mercy on the ſame account.</p>
            <p>But ſtill I deſire you to take notice, that tho' theſe four <hi>Pleas</hi> now mentioned, are Arguments againſt our utter deſtruction, yet they are no Pleas againſt our temporal Correction and Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. But rather indeed, the abuſes of our ſingular Mercies and Priviledges, do not only plead but cry for our puniſhment, even before others, as 'tis ſaid, <hi>Amos</hi> 3. 2. <hi>You only have I known of all the Families upon Earth, therefore I will puniſh you for all your Iniquities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed when I conſider what a Favourite <hi>People</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> once were, and by what a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful deſtruction they were cut off at the laſt. I am ſure <hi>Favourite England</hi> has reaſon to look about her. The rather alas! in that by the Death of our late moſt Excellent <hi>Queen (of whom</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:93565:15"/> 
               <hi>the World was not worthy)</hi> God ſeems to have <hi>made a way to his anger:</hi> by removing that <hi>extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Princeſs</hi> out of the Nation, he has taken up one chief <hi>Barrier</hi> of his wrath. I cannot but look on this as the moſt angry <hi>Blow</hi> that ever I knew given to theſe <hi>Three Nations,</hi> and perhaps to many more. Let us then turn immediately and unfeignedly to him that hath ſmitten us, whilſt our wounds are capable of being healed. A little longer continuance in ſin may make our ruine inevitable. As <hi>Judah ſin'd till there was no remedy,</hi> 2 Chron 36. 16.</p>
            <p>Thus having conſider'd the parts of my Text in a practical manner all along: I ſhall now only lay a few Inferences before you ſuitable to the whole, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p>I. <hi>Inf.</hi> As we expect a ſtable and ſettled Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Peace, we muſt be heartily and ſteddily religious. If we were in truth <hi>God's People,</hi> we ſhould be <hi>his Inheritance,</hi> which he would defend againſt all Invaders. But if we are but <hi>ſuperficial Chriſtians,</hi> we can have but an <hi>imaginary happineſs.</hi> For, if Vice raves as it has done: If Blaſphemy and Villany triumph: If every day produces new Oaths, and new Methods of Luſt: And if the Ways of <hi>God</hi> are exploded, and Truth, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity fails from among the Children of Men, alas! what woe, what miſery awaits us?</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:93565:16"/>
            <p> Let us therefore look that our <hi>Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> may have reformed Votaries: and that our <hi>Lives</hi> become the viſible Tranſcript of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and <hi>undefiled Faith.</hi> Then ſhall we proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and flouriſh indeed, and be truly and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily great, and not till then.</p>
            <p>II <hi>Inf</hi> See we, who are Enemies to a Nations Peace and Proſperity, and who are worthy to feel the ſharpneſs of the <hi>Magiſtrates Sword, viz.</hi> Such as offend the God of all Victory and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs. <hi>Achan's Sins</hi> did more miſchief to <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Camp, than all their <hi>Army</hi> could do good. And if we grant, that there is the ſame <hi>all-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God</hi> in Heaven, we muſt needs perceive our ſelves in danger of being blaſted from the ſame Cauſe? or rather, <hi>are we not blaſted already?</hi> yet <hi>who lays it to heart?</hi> Did the moſt Aged of us ever before know <hi>Earthquakes</hi> ſo frequent, <hi>Sea-ſtorms</hi> ſo fatal, and <hi>Wars</hi> ſo univerſal, and of ſo long continuance? Yet <hi>who amongſt us turns to him that ſmiteth us?</hi> But on the contrary, is not the Name of the <hi>Great and Terrible God more propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned than ever?</hi> Are not the Prayers of a few De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourt Perſons in this Land countermined by the volleys of Oaths and Curſes of innumerable Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers? Are not our ears filled with the <hi>hideous imprecations of Damnation,</hi> as we paſs the ſtreets?
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93565:16"/> This is ſurely the moſt <hi>monſtrous ſin</hi> that ever the Earth bore. God has been diſhonoured in all Ages, but he was never ſo <hi>dared and challenged</hi> as he is in this.</p>
            <p>For ſhame, ceaſe your blaſpheming Inſults, ye Monſters of Iniquity! Know aſſuredly that <hi>your Damnation lingers not,</hi> ye need not haſten it The ſtreams of flaming Brimſtone will fill your mouths ſoon enough, ye need not call to your <hi>Judge</hi> to make ſpeed with his work. But it behoves you rather to fall on your knees, and unſay what you have ſaid; for your Curſes will otherwiſe be <hi>poured like burning Oyle into your Bones,</hi> Pſal. 109. 18.</p>
            <p>We have all of us reaſon to oppoſe you in this; for, <hi>by reaſon of your Swearing the Land mourns,</hi> Jer. 23. 10.</p>
            <p>But in this our <hi>mournful Caſe,</hi> 'tis not a little comfortable to us; That the Supream Authority has teſtified its diſlike of <hi>Prophane Swearing and Curſing</hi> by a <hi>new Law to puniſh it.</hi> And may we all in our ſtations acquit our Conſciences in fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering the juſt execution of it. For, as this is the moſt common and moſt defenſeleſs ſin, it deſerves to fall in the firſt place, as a <hi>Preſage</hi> (we hope) of the <hi>Fall</hi> of all other Enormities after it.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:93565:17"/>
            <p> This minds us of <hi>zealous Moſes</hi> again; the <hi>Example</hi> I have propoſed all along. We muſt now conſider him as a <hi>Chief Magiſtrate,</hi> and we ſee with what impartiality he executed Juſtice on ſuch as offended in matter of the <hi>Golden-Calf,</hi> to which the Text relates. For <hi>he regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed neither Relation nor Friend,</hi> but (by his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers) ſlew all that were convicted of it, to the number of <hi>three thouſand Perſons, Exod.</hi> 32. 28. and then <hi>God was entreated</hi> for the reſt.</p>
            <p>I therefore turn me with due reſpect to the <hi>Worſhipful Magiſtrates</hi> of this Great City. <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen,</hi> I ſpeak in <hi>the Name of the Great God to you,</hi> of a thing, in which his honour and the common good is greatly concerned. As <hi>God</hi> has put his <hi>Sword</hi> into your hands <hi>for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Wickedneſs</hi> and Vice, and the protection of Vertue and Innocence, even ſo draw it forth effectually <hi>for the Lord's ſake.</hi> Oh! what a Field of Honour lies before you! you may do more for the glory of God, by one exemplary Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhmment of Prophaneneſs than we can by a Volume of Sermons againſt it. Many Perſons have ſin'd themſelves to an utter obduracy in Spiritual things, they are inſenſible of reproof, their <hi>Faith is dead,</hi> and their <hi>Conſcience ſeared:</hi> But their Senſes are alive, and 'tis you only that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93565:17"/> can touch them in their moſt ſenſible Parts, their <hi>Bodies</hi> and their <hi>Purſes:</hi> Oh! make theſe Rampant Sinners know, that you <hi>hold not the Sword of Magiſtracy in vain.</hi> Can it be any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger endured, that Women (to whom it would be ſhame enough to be ſolicited) ſhould ſolicit Men to Uncleanneſs in the open Streets, even before the Noon-day Sun? Can we longer bear the Wounds which <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> and <hi>Obſcenity</hi> make in our Ears as we paſs along? Is it not time that thoſe vain People be undeceiv'd, who think themſelves advanced in <hi>Greatneſs and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility</hi> by the height of their Vices?</p>
            <p>Oh! what can be more Divinely Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and more abſolutely neceſſary, than to fix reſolvedly on the <hi>Reformation</hi> of theſe crying En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ormities, which would at once advance the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, retrieve the Reputation of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, diſpel the Cauſes of our Ruine in Church and State, ſettle the peace of our Conſciences, and tend to our everlaſting happineſs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reformation</hi> is a Work ſo Divine, ſo Glorious, ſo Bleſſed, that were it the work of the Saints above (as it is of thoſe below) we might well think that <hi>Moſes</hi> would gladly come down from the <hi>Heavenly Mount Zion,</hi> as he did from the Mount in the Context, to bring Men to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93565:18"/> acquaintance with the ways of God. But we are told from Heaven that a <hi>Man ariſing from the Dead</hi> is no proper Inſtrument to reclaim Sinners. The Anſwer is, <hi>they have Moſes and the Prophets already,</hi> Luke 16. 29. We have indeed their Writings, Oh! that we had their Spirit too, or rather <hi>a double Portion of it,</hi> to check the invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Prophaneneſs of the Aged World. For, I take it to be an unqueſtionable Truth, and I pray God fix it deeply in our Minds and Hearts: That <hi>there is no more hope of our ſolid Proſperity, than there is of our real Reformation.</hi> It was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet known, that <hi>ſuch mercies</hi> as we enjoy, and <hi>ſuch ſins</hi> as we commit, continued long to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>III <hi>Inf.</hi> Laſtly, we may hence diſcover one Reaſon of the ſlowneſs of our ſucceſs againſt the <hi>common Enemy, viz.</hi> Our unfitneſs for ſuch a Mercy. Were our Enemies entirely ſubdued, we might probably grow worſe; For, <hi>our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies have hitherto ripned our Sins,</hi> and therefore (till we are better diſpoſed for <hi>Deliverance and Victory,)</hi> mercy it ſelf cannot but keep it from us; or diſpenſe it (as a <hi>Phyſician</hi> does fleſh-meat to a crazy Conſtitution) very rarely, and in ſmall Portions. So that the Divine Goodneſs may be ſuppoſed to ſigh over us, as once over
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93565:18"/> 
               <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſay: <hi>Oh that my People had hearkned unto me! that Iſrael had walk'd in my ways, I ſhould ſoon have ſubdued their Enemies, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned my hand againſt their Adverſaries.</hi> Pſal. 81. 13. So that we here ſee, the readieſt way to make a <hi>ſpeedy end</hi> of our <hi>long War.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſee then, my beloved Brethren, wherein lyes our direct and only Path to the Temporal Proſperity of our Nation, as well as the Eternal happineſs of our Souls: Namely, in a general and unfeigned return to God, in true Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for paſt Sins, and in caſting away from us that Prophaneneſs, Bitterneſs, Diviſion, and Hypocriſie, whereby God has been ſo long of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended and diſhonoured, ſerving the Lord with <hi>fervency of Spirit</hi> in <hi>newneſs of Life</hi> for the time to come. For it is impoſſible that we ſhould be happy here or hereafter without the Favour and Bleſſing of God: And it is alſo impoſſible to attain the Favour of God whilſt we continue in our Impieties. Why ſhould we then any longer <hi>delay to keep God's Commandments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you'll ſay perhaps, This is that we are doing this Day. The whole Nation is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be at their Prayers this Day, and to humble themſelves before our offended God, and ſeek his Favour. In a General Faſt, every
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93565:19"/> one is (in ſome ſenſe) to <hi>gird himſelf with Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, and lie in the Duſt;</hi> and repent and reform, in order to purge away the National Guilt.</p>
            <p>To this I Anſwer; Oh! that it were ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; I wiſh with all the Concern I am able, that there were ſuch a General Repentance this Day amongſt us, as we extreamly need, even to the laſt neceſſity. But ah! may it not here be reply'd, as <hi>Samuel</hi> once did, to convince a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Piety of real Iniquity, (1 Sam. 15. 14.) <hi>What meaneth then this bleating of the Sheep in mine Ears; and the lowing of Oxen which I hear?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus as to our Caſe, What meaneth the ratling of idle Coaches in our Ears, and the tramplings of the Horſes of ſuch as ride abroad to divert themſelves? What means the noiſe of Buſineſs, and Vanity, yea of Lewdneſs in the Streets? Do the open preparations in the But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher's and Cook's Shops, denote the ſelf denial of a Faſt, or the Entertainment of a Feſtival? Do the Modern gariſh Dreſſes bear any reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance to the <hi>Scriptural Sackcloath?</hi> Yea, do not ſome amongſt us mock our Faſts, and defame the Obſervers of them? And alas! may it not hence be feared (or rather conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) with too great reaſon, that a ſort of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93565:19"/> 
               <hi>Perverſe Spirit</hi> is fallen upon us, like that of the <hi>Jews,</hi> a little before their Captivity, which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed (Iſa. 22. 12, 13.) <hi>In that day did the Lord God of Hoſts call to weeping, and to mourning, and to bald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to girding with Sackcloth, (i. e.</hi> to the moſt ſolemn and ſevere humiliation and ſelf-abaſement:) <hi>And behold Joy and Gladneſs, ſlaying of Oxen, and killing of Sheep; eating of Fleſh and drinking of Wine: Let us eat and drink for to morrow we ſhall dye.</hi> Here was a perfect Scheme of Epicuriſm, in times when God called both by his Prophets and Providences to bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mourning, and ſorrow of Heart. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, what Ear can without tingling, hear that which follows in that Propheſie? Or what Heart can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trembling and terror conſider it? (verſ. 14.) <hi>And it was revealed in mine Ears by the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> (the God whom they mockt, and whoſe Calls they deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,) <hi>Surely this Iniquity ſhall not be purged from you till ye die, i. e.</hi> this Daring, Mocking Obſtinacy of yours, will and ſhall be your Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Oh! may no ſhare of this Guilt, no ſpark of this Wrath, befall us or our Nation. May we all be numbered amongſt thoſe that <hi>mourn now</hi> in hope of the promiſed Conſolation, <hi>(Luk.</hi> 6. 21.) rather than after a little empty and unſeaſonable merriment, go down to the place of <hi>Everlaſting Weeping and Wail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:93565:20"/> (verſ. 25.) Be we aſſured that God obſerves the Frame of every one of our Souls this day; and will perhaps ſignalize the ſecret Mourner for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Sins, by a peculiar exemption in the Day of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, as it was in a like Caſe, (Ezek. 9. 4.) <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto him, go thorow the midſt of the City, thorow the midſt of Jeruſalem, and ſet a Mark upon the Foreheads of the Men that ſigh and that cry for all the abominations that be done in the midſt thereof.</hi> And this Mark was to be to them a note of Divine Protection from the Beſom of Deſtruction whereby others were ſwept away: Juſt as the <hi>Blood of the Paſcal Lamb</hi> on the Door-poſts of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> was their ſecurity from that Plague whereby the Firſt-born of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> were deſtroy'd.</p>
            <p>But as for ſuch who never yet kept a Faſt in that contrite, humble and affecting manner which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by God: But deal by this, as by all other parts of Religion. If a little formal and lifeleſs obſervance of it will ſerve the turn, they will be for it as loudly as any: But more than this is over-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them. Theſe, I ſay, do rather cumber the Work of this day than forward it. They deny God their Heart, and therefore give him nothing. And as Religion has no Hold of them, ſo they can have no Benefit from it. They are for a Religion
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93565:20"/> that will coſt them nothing, but this will appear a Religion which they can get nothing by.</p>
            <p>May we then from this day forward turn to the Lord our God with all our Heart, and ſerve Him with all our might. That it may be ſaid of this Faſt of ours, as it was of that Effectual <hi>Faſt of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neve</hi> (Jon. 3. 10.) <hi>And God ſaw their Works, that they turn'd from their Evil ways: And he repented of the Evil that he ſaid he would do unto them, and did it not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I therefore humbly beſeech the God of all Grace, to kindle a moſt Ardent Zeal for his Ways in every one of us, and make us indeed an <hi>Holy People;</hi> that the <hi>Holy God</hi> may (with Honour) ſave and defend us, as <hi>his People, and his Inheritance;</hi> and continue to deliver us (as he lately did) <hi>with a Mighty Hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in order to the <hi>Repoſe and Renown</hi> of theſe <hi>Kingdoms:</hi> May it pleaſe <hi>Almighty Goodneſs</hi> to proſper His <hi>Majeſty's Forces</hi> by Sea and Land, in the Juſt-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of all that's dear to us. May his <hi>Great Affairs</hi> every where be favoured with the Divine Bleſſing.</p>
            <p>And above all, may it pleaſe God to preſerve his <hi>Royal Perſon,</hi> the <hi>Breath of our Noſtrils:</hi> That under his ſhade we may continue to breathe our Free Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive-air.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93565:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> Free, I ſay, from all the <hi>Fogs and Plagues of the Spiritual Egypt.</hi> That being bleſt with the Cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Beams of the <hi>Holy Goſpel,</hi> we may rejoice in the Experience of God's Mercy here, and in the Hope of a perfect Enjoyment of it for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now to him that is able to Save and Defend us, and to do more for us than we can ask or think: To Him be Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Praiſe, Dominion and Obedience aſcribed for ever and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
